Register of the Charles Wellington Furlong Papers, 1917-1963
Hoover Institution Archives
Charles Wellington Furlong Papers,
1917-1963
63017
Furlong, Charles Wellington, 1874-1967
10 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize portfolio, 9 envelopes (5.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, writings, clippings, maps, and photographs, relating to Woodrow Wilson, the Paris Peace Conference, military, political, and economic conditions in the Balkans (particularly relating to Fiume and Montenegro), the Tacna-Arica dispute between Peru and Chile, and the work of the Tacna-Arica Plebiscitary Commission, 1925-1926.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1963.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924.; Paris Peace Conference (1919-1920); Tacna-Arica question.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Peace.; Balkan Peninsula.; Chile.; Chile--Foreign relations--Peru.; Rijeka (Croatia); Croatia.; Italy.; Italy--Foreign relations--Yugoslavia.; Montenegro.; Peru.; Peru--Foreign relations--Chile.; United States--Foreign relations.; Yugoslavia.; Yugoslavia--Foreign relations--Italy.; Yugoslavia--History--1918-1945.
Biographical Note
1895 Graduated, Massachusetts Normal Art School
1901-1902 Student, Cornell, Harvard, Ecole des Beaux Arts, Paris
1896-1904 Faculty, Cornell
1909 Author, The Gateway to the Sahara
1911 Author, Tripoli in Barbary
1914-1918 General Staff, U.S. Army
1918-1919 Member, American Peace delegation, Paris
1919 Special Military aide to President Woodrow Wilson
1919 Military observer, intelligence officer in the Balkans, Near East and Middle East
1921 Author, Let 'er Buck
1926 Member, Tacna-Arica Commission
1967 Died
Series Description
- Correspondence, 1917-1963 (Box No. 1.)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
- Subject File, 1917-1936. (Box No. 2-8.)
  Reports, memoranda, printed material, clippings, etc. arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
- Speeches and Writings, 1919-1926. (Box No. 9.)
  Drafts, notes, typescripts of reports, articles by Charles W. Furlong, arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
- Map. (On Shelf.)
  1 oversize map of Austrian and Montenegran forces, 1915.
- Audio-visual.
  See photo card catalog.
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1917-1963
  - General, 1919-1926 (Box 1.)
  - Unidentified, 1919-1926
  - Andrews, Admiral Philip, 1919
  - Austin, T. A., Jr., 1926
  - Babbitt, E. B., 1918
  - Baikovitch, Stevan, 1919
  - Baker, Ray Stannard, 1922
  - Barker, Captain, 1928
  - Benuzzi, Valerio and Charlotte, 1919
  - Bingaman, Joseph W., 1963
  - Bouritch, Mr., 1919
  - Brown, Mauricio, 1926
  - Bruce, James, 1919-1935
  - Buckey, Colonel M. C., 1919
  - Churchill, General M., 1919
  - Claro, Samuel, 1926
  - Cullen, Frederick L., 1926
  - Cumberpatch, James T., 1926
  - Cusani, Viscount L., 1919
  - Dantras, Victor, 1919
  - Day, Murray, 1928
  - Dennis, William Cullen, 1926
  - Dillard, W. R., 1919
  - Early, A. D., 1918
  - Edwards, Augustin, n.d.
  - Fliess, Felipe, 1926
  - Foster, Manuel, 1926
  - Franck, Harry A., 1919
  - Frederickson, Lieutenant, 1919
  - Furlong, Frank, 1919
  - Grayson, Admiral Cary T., 1920
  - Hoffer, George (?) W., n.d.
  - Hopkins, T. C., n.d.
  - Hunter, W. J., 1919
  - Jay, Peter A., 1926
  - Jevtitch, Monsieur B., 1929
  - Joitch, R., 1918-1919
  - Jusserand, J. J., n.d.
  - Kellogg, Frank B., 1925
  - Kreger, E. A., 1926
  - Krstelj, Dr., 1919
  - Lassiter, W., 1926
  - Leroyer, J., 1918
  - McLean, Philip T., 1963
  - Maira, Manuel, 1926
  - Marshall, E., 1925
  - Martin, Gerald, 1927-1931
  - Milo, Prince of Montenegro, 1935-1936
  - Mitchich, D., 1919
  - Nikaj, Don Antonio, 1919
  - Pershing, General John J., 1925
  - Plamenac, J. S., 1919
  - Plesnicov, Milan, 1919
  - Powell, Mr., 1918 (?)
  - Prince, John, n.d.
  - Radovitch, Andre, 1919
  - Rice, Lyman, 1919
  - Russell, C. V., 1926
  - Salommn, A., 1926
  - Sanders, Edgar, 1928
  - Savy, General, 1919
  - Schaefer, J. Louis, 1926
  - Simovitch, Svetislav, 1919
  - Smith, Lieutenant, 1919
  - Street, Lionel A. B., 1919-1935
  - Sullivan, A. N., 1926
  - Tahon, General, 1919
  - Thwaites, Norman, 1935
  - Toombs, L. A., 1919
  - Tuckerman, Edward, 1920
  - Violette, Mr., 1917
  - Wilson, President Woodrow, 1920
  - Wisety, Professor, 1919
  - Zilioty, Luigi, n.d.
  - Miscellany
- SUBJECT FILE, 1917-1936
  - Albania (Box 2.)
  - Biographical material
    - Awards
    - Miscellany
    - News clippings
    - Recommendations, passed, etc.
  - Bristol, Admiral
  - Buckey, Colonel M. C.
  - Cohn, Louis
  - Comitadji question
  - Czecholovakia
  - Czernin, Count Ottorkar
  - Dalmatia
  - D'Annunzio, Gabriele
  - Esterhazy, Franciscus
  - European War, 1914-1918
  - Explorer's Club
  - Fez
  - Finland
  - Fiume (Rijeka)
  - France
  - Greece
  - Istria
  - Italian-Yugoslavian relations
  - Italy
  - Larcovic, Ivan
  - Maroc (Morocco)
  - Mazuranic, Vladimir
  - Milutinovich, General D.
  - Miscellany
  - Montenegro (Box 3.)
    - General
      - Interviews
      - Memoranda
      - Printed material
      - Reports
      - Reports by British officers
      - Reports by Charles Furlong
    - Allied troops
    - American Red Cross
    - Baikovitch, Stevan
    - Cavalry
    - Cervione War Camp
    - Committee of Refugees
    - Damyanovitch, Lazar
    - Kamenarovitch, Cyr
    - Lovtchen
    - Mijatovic, Marko
    - Milo, Prince of Montenegro
    - Miscellany
    - National Assembly
    - Nicolas, King of Montenegro
    - Paris Peace Conference, 1919
    - Petrovich-Niegosch (Genealogical table)
    - Plamenatz, Yovan
    - Plamenatz, Madame
    - Political parties
    - Popovich, Krsto
    - Popovich, Marko Z.
    - Popovich, Vladimir G.
    - St. Basile Monastery
    - "Song of the Ljesanin Guard" (Montenegrin separatist song)
    - Towns and cities
  - Montenegrin organizations in America
  - Morocco (Box 4.)
  - New York Herald Tribune, 1918-1919 (incomplete)
  - Paris Peace Conference
    - General
      - Maps
      - Miscellany
      - Newspaper clippings
    - American Commission to Negotiate Peace
  - Powell, E. Alexander
  - Radich, Stephan (Box 5.)
  - Radovitch, Andre
  - Red Cross, American
  - Rodovitch, Stevan
  - Scutari
  - Sempre Avanti, January, 1922 (Italian-American magazine)
  - Senoussi, Sheik
  - Serbia
  - Serbia and Eastern Russia, 4 vols., Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1918
  - Syria
  - Tacna-Arica dispute
    - General
      - Forms, ballots, petitions
      - Miscellany
      - Notes by Charles Furlong
      - Printed material (Box 6.)
    - American mediation
    - Arica
    - Chile-Peru relations
    - Deitrick, Jackie
    - Diccionario Plebiscitario (Plebiscitary Dictionary)
    - Edwards, Augustin
    - History
    - Opinion and Award of the Arbitrator, July 20, 1922
    - Pershing, General John J.
    - Plebicitary Commission
      - Background material
      - Charts
      - Maps
      - Memorabilia (Box 7.)
      - Memoranda
      - Notebook by Charles Furlong
    - Plebiscite
    - Press review, March 23, 1926 -June 17, 1926
    - Registration and election boards
    - Resolution (Box 8.)
    - South Pacific Mail
    - Stuart, Graham H.
    - Tacna
    - Wambaugh, Sarah
    - West Coast Leader
    - Thurn and Taxis, Prince
  - Trieste
  - U.S. Naval Radio Press, July 1919 (incomplete)
  - U.S.S. George Washington, voyage to Europe, 1918
  - Verdun
  - Versailles Treaty - bibliography
  - Vouksanovitch, Radosar
  - Wilson, President Woodrow
  - Yugoslavia
  - Zara
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1919-1926
  - General. Miscellaneous notes (Box 9.)
  - "The Alsace-Lorraine of South America," 1926 October 9. One photocopy
  - "History and Opinion of the Tacna-Arica Plebiscite," undated. One carbon copy
  - Montenegro manuscript (unpublished), 1935?.
    - Cover design. One pencil drawing, one ink drawing
    - Notes. Typewritten and printed. [Five folders]
    - Drafts. Typewritten and carbon copy pages, some with hand annotations [Seven folders]
    - Drafts. Typewritten and carbon copy pages, some with hand annotations [One folder] (Box 10.)
  - "On an Expedition from Hooe Barracks to Versailliski," Monograph 23, undated. One hand-printed, handmade booklet
  - "Preliminary Report on the Montenegrin Situation," 1919. Two copies (1 typewritten, 1 carbon), with photographs. Slightly different versions on the same topic [Two folders]
  - "Statement of Status and Proposal for a Potential Settlement of the Tacna-Arica Problem," undated. One carbon copy
- MAP.
  - 1 oversize map of Austrian and Montenegrin forces, 1915
- AUDIO-VISUAL.
  - See photo card catalog